本片含有成人内容 粗野用语和暴力画面
请酌情观看
纪录片之家
倾情奉献
Coming home from Vietnam was
从越南回到国内
close to as traumatic as the war itself.
就跟在越南打仗一样难受
For years, nobody talked about Vietnam.
许多年来 没有人谈论越南的事
We were friends with a young couple
我们有一对年轻的夫妇朋友
and it was only after 12 years that the two wives were talking.
但认识12年后 双方妻子才在交谈中
Found out that we both had been Marines in Vietnam.
发现我们两位丈夫都曾在越南当过陆战队员
卡尔·马兰提斯
陆战队
Never said a word about it.
从来就没说到这事
Never mentioned it.
从来都不提及这事
And the whole country was like that.
而整个国家就都像是这样
It was so divisive.
真是太分裂扭曲了
And it's like living in a family with an alcoholic father.
这就像是住在一个有酒鬼老爸的家里
"Shh, we don't talk about that."
"嘘 我们不能说这个"
Our country did that with Vietnam.
我们国家就是这样对待越战的
It's only been very recently that, I think, that,
我想是直到最近不久
you know, the baby boomers are finally starting to say,
婴儿潮那一代的人终于开始问道
"What happened?
"发生了什么
What happened?"
究竟发生了什么"
What we need now in this country
现在我们国家所需要的
is to heal the wounds
就是愈合创伤
and to put Vietnam behind us.
并把越南抛到身后
The killing in this tragic war must stop.
这场悲剧性战争里的杀戮必须停止了
General Westmoreland's strategy
威斯特摩兰将军的策略
is producing results.
正在产生效果了
The enemy is no longer closer to victory.
敌人不再更接近于胜利了
No matter how you measure it,
不管你们是怎么看的
we're better off than we thought we would be at this time.
我们此时的境况比预期的要乐观得多
You have been less than candid
你没有很坦诚地说明
as to how deeply we are involved in Vietnam.
我们在多大程度上介入了越南
We have increased our assistance
我们增派了援助
to the government, its logistics.
给那边的政府及其后勤
We have not sent combat troops there.
我们没有派作战部队去那里
You have a row of dominoes set up
现在有着一连串的多米诺骨牌
and you knock over the first one and the last one,
你推倒了第一块和最后一块牌
certainly it will go over.
那么它肯定会倾倒
If aggression is successful in Korea,
如果他们成功入侵了韩国
we can expect it to spread throughout Asia and Europe
那我们就等着赤潮传遍亚洲和欧洲
and to this hemisphere.
传到我们这个半球吧
越南战争
Viktor Frankl, who survived the death camps in World War II,
维克多·弗兰克从二战的集中营里幸存了下来
wrote a book called Man's Search for Meaning.
他写了本书叫《活出意义来》
You know, "To live is to suffer.
他说 "人活着就是一种折磨
To survive is to find meaning in suffering."
人要活下来则是要在这种痛苦里找到生存的意义"
And for those of us who suffered because of Vietnam,
对于我们这些深受越战折磨的人
麦克斯·克里兰
陆军
that's been our quest ever since.
这句话便成了我们的追求
America's involvement in Vietnam began in secrecy.
美国一开始是秘密介入越南事务的
It ended, 30 years later, in failure,
并在30年后以失败告终
witnessed by the entire world.
且整个世界有目共睹
It was begun in good faith by decent people
这一切都始于光鲜体面的人们
out of fateful misunderstandings,
满怀真心 却又严重误解
American overconfidence, and Cold War miscalculation.
以及美国的过度自信和冷战误判
And it was prolonged
而它如此拖延
because it seemed easier to muddle through
则是因为蒙混过关似乎要好过
than admit that it had been caused by tragic decisions,
承认它是始于两大政党的
made by five American presidents,
5位美国总统的
belonging to both political parties.
悲剧性决定
Before the war was over,
在越战结束前
more than 58,000 Americans would be dead.
有5.8万多美国人死亡
At least 250,000 South Vietnamese troops
至少25万南越军队
died in the conflict, as well.
也死于这场冲突
So did over a million North Vietnamese soldiers
还有100万的北越士兵和越共游击队员
and Viet Cong guerrillas.
也死于其中
Two million civilians, north and south,
南北共有200万平民
are thought to have perished,
可能也灰飞烟灭了
as well as tens of thousands more
还有邻国老挝和柬埔寨的
in the neighboring states of Laos and Cambodia.
成千上万人也都就此消亡
For many Vietnamese,
对许多越南人来说
it was a brutal civil war;
这是一场残酷的内战
for others, the bloody climactic chapter
对其他人而言 这是百年独立斗争中的
in a century-old struggle for independence.
血腥高潮篇章
For those Americans who fought in it,
对于出国参战的美国人
and for those who fought against it back home,
以及国内反战的美国人
as well as for those who merely glimpsed it on the nightly news,
还有那些只在夜间新闻瞥上一眼的人们
the Vietnam War was a decade of agony,
越战是一场十年的痛苦挣扎
the most divisive period since the Civil War.
也是自内战后最为分裂的时期
Vietnam seemed to call everything into question...
越南似乎使得一切都陷入了质疑中
the value of honor and gallantry;
荣誉与勇气的价值
the qualities of cruelty and mercy;
残暴与仁慈的品质
the candor of the American government;
美国政府的坦诚
and what it means to be a patriot.
以及爱国者的真正含义
And those who lived through it
历经了这事的人们
have never been able to erase its memory,
一直都无法将之忘怀
have never stopped arguing about what really happened,
一直都未停止争辩究竟发生了什么
why everything went so badly wrong,
为什么一切会变得如此严重错误
who was to blame,
谁该为此担责
and whether it was all worth it.
这一切是否值得
已经40年过去了
但是越南的老兵们
我们也不想谈论那场战争
人们歌颂胜利 歌颂自由 他们都错了
谁赢谁输并不重要
在战争中没有赢家或输家
包宁
北越军队
只有破坏和毁灭
只有那些没打过仗的人们
才喜欢争论谁赢谁输
第一集
似曾相识
法国在19世纪中期攻占了我们的国家
那场入侵既血腥又残酷
包宁
北越军队
The French conquest of Indochina began with
法国队印度支那的征服始于
an attack on the ancient Vietnamese port of Danang in 1858.
1858年对越南古老港口岘港的攻占
It took 50 years to lay claim to the whole region...
法国用了50年才占有了这整个地区
Laos and Cambodia,
有老挝 有柬埔寨
as well as the 1,200-mile-long area
还有一片1200英里长的区域
that would come to be called Vietnam.
这就是后来所称的越南
All of it was ruled by a French governor-general
这整个地区都由法国总督所统治
from his palace in Hanoi.
而他的宫殿就在河内
The French largely lived on plantation estates,
法国人在很大程度上靠种植园过活
and in cities, like Saigon,
而像西贡之类的城市
made to look as much as possible like those at home.
也尽量造得像法国的一样
Most did not even bother to learn the language
他们多数人甚至都不用去学
spoken by their subjects.
自己臣民所讲的语言
Instead they installed a series of puppet emperors
相反他们扶植了一系列的傀儡皇帝
and employed a network of French-speaking Vietnamese officials...
并网罗了一堆讲法语的越南人官员
mandarins...
当然这些官吏们
willing to carry out their wishes.
得愿意为法国人进行统治
The French put their subjects to work
法国人利用民众来干活
building roads and canals,
建造道路 运河
railroads and bridges.
铁路和桥梁
法国人当然自夸自擂于
他们为越南人民所带来的文明
越南人当然不需要法国的文明
他们需要的是独立
The Vietnamese people did not take easily to French occupation,
越南人民对于法国人的占领可没服服帖帖的
just as they had fought against earlier invasions by the Chinese.
毕竟他们之前就已经抵抗过中国人的入侵了
By the early 20th century, nationalism was on the rise.
到20世纪早期 民族主义风头正盛
But anyone who dared resist colonial rule
但是任何胆敢抵抗殖民统治的人
risked exile, prison, or the guillotine.
都会面临着流亡 入狱 甚至砍头
他们控制了一切
控制我们国家的一切资源
但最重要的是 他们夺走了我们的独立
夺走了我们的自由
当我还是小孩时 我就已在学校里萌生了民族主义
陈玉泉
南越陆战队
我总是将法国人视作敌人
我的敌人
对法国人来说 越南人就是一个次等民族
在越南 没有平等可言
林光世
南越军队
所以我们才如此痛恨他们
My hatred for them was pure.
我对他们的痛恨是纯粹的
Pure.
纯粹的
约翰·马斯格雷夫
陆战队
I hated them so much.
我是那么地痛恨他们
And I was so scared of them.
我也那么地害怕他们
Boy, I was terrified of them.
我实在是被他们吓坏了
And the scareder I got, the more I hated them.
我越怕他们 我就越恨他们
I was an 18-year-old Marine rifleman
我那时是个18岁的陆战队步枪兵
with the ink still wet on my high school diploma.
我的高中毕业证上的墨水都还没干呢
I didn't want to shame myself in front of my buddies.
我不想在队友面前丢脸
But I was so scared.
但我实在是很害怕
I felt like I was hanging onto my honor by my fingernails
我觉得自己在那里的全部时候都是为了
the whole time I was there.
保住自己的荣誉
In the Spring of 1919,
在1919年春天
as the victorious Allied Powers met in Paris
战胜的协约国各方汇聚巴黎
to rebuild a world shattered by the Great War,
重建一战后的残破世界
President Woodrow Wilson headed the American delegation
美国总统伍德罗·威尔逊率领代表团
housed in the Hotel Crillon.
入驻柯立龙酒店
One day, a tall, slender, 29-year-old man
某天 有名高高瘦瘦的29岁男子
appeared with a petition for the president
带着一份请愿书前来交给总统
he and other Vietnamese nationalists had written.
他和一些越南民族主义者写了这份请愿
Inspired by Wilson's declaration
威尔逊的声明鼓舞了他
that the interests of colonial peoples should be given
总统说殖民地人民的利益应该得到
equal weight with those of their European rulers,
与欧洲统治者同等分量的重视
the man was asking that this principle be applied to his homeland.
这男子请求将此原则应用于他的祖国
The president's secretary promised to show it to Wilson,
总统秘书承诺说会转交给威尔逊看的
but there is no evidence that he ever did.
但没有证据表明他兑现了这一承诺
His name was Nguyen Tat Thanh,
那名男子叫做 阮必成
but he was now living under an alias, Nguyen Ai Quoc...
不过这时他用的是化名 阮爱国
"Nguyen the Patriot."
爱国者的意思
During his long, shadowy career,
在他漫长而神秘的生涯里
he would adopt some 70 different pseudonyms,
他共用过约70个不同的化名
finally settling on "the most enlightened one"...
最后固定用了个 "最具启发性的"
Ho Chi Minh.
胡志明
Ho Chi Minh was a man who
胡志明这个人
succeeded in projecting an image of somebody
他成功地给自己营造了一个形象
who was totally dedicated to freeing his country and his people
他完全献身于将自己的国家和人民
from foreign domination
从外国统治中解放出来
to the point that he sacrificed his own well-being, his own life,
甚至还牺牲了自己的个人幸福和生活
not having a family of his own.
他没有自己的家庭
To Vietnamese, that's a big sacrifice
在越南人看来  这是很大的牺牲
杨文麦
河内
because to us everybody needs a family.
因为我们每个人都需要有个家庭
Ho Chi Minh was born in 1890,
胡志明生于1890年
the son of a minor official in the French regime.
他是法国政权里的一名小官的儿子
After taking part in a demonstration against the puppet emperor
因为参加示威反对傀儡皇帝
and the Frenchmen who pulled his strings,
及其背后的法国势力
Ho was expelled from school and marked for arrest.
胡志明被学校开除并成为逃犯
He left Vietnam in 1911 and remained in exile for 30 years.
他于1911年离开越南并流亡了30年
He served as a cook's helper aboard a French liner,
他登上一艘法国邮轮并当上了帮厨
and visited New York and Boston,
还到过纽约和波士顿
where he worked for a time as a pastry chef at the Parker House.
并在这里的帕克豪斯酒店当了一段时间的糕点师傅
He shoveled snow in London,
他在伦敦铲过雪
tinted photographs in Paris.
在巴黎洗印过照片
There, Ho Chi Minh joined the French Socialist Party.
胡志明在那里加入了法国社会党
But when he discovered the anti-colonial writings of Lenin,
不过在发现了列宁的反殖民论述后
he became a communist.
他就成为了一名共产主义者
He was invited to Moscow to study,
他被邀请到莫斯科进行学习
underwent training as a Soviet agent,
并接受训练成为了苏联特工
was sometimes criticized for being a nationalist first,
有时他还被批评说先是个民族主义者
a communist second,
然后才是个共产主义者
and then was dispatched to China
然后他被派到了中国
to organize a cell of other Vietnamese exiles
组织起了一堆越南流亡分子
and help establish the Indochinese Communist Party.
并帮忙建立了印度支那共产党
Through it all,
从始至终
"He was taut and quivering,"
"他兢兢业业 谨小慎微"
a friend remembered,
朋友这样回忆道
"with only one thought...
"心中只有一个念头
his country, Vietnam."
他的国家 越南"
By 1940, much of the world was at war again.
到1940年 世界上大部分地方又陷入了战争
Germany had seized most of Western Europe,
德国攻占了大部分西欧
including France.
法国也沦陷了
Imperial Japan threatened
日本帝国威胁到了
many of the European colonies in Asia,
欧洲在亚洲的许多殖民地
and occupied Vietnam,
并占领了越南
where they permitted their allies, the collaborationist French,
他们允许已经投降的法国盟友
to continue to oversee their colony.
继续监管他们的殖民地
To some Vietnamese,
对有些越南人来说
the coming of the Japanese seemed to signal
日本人的到来似乎可喜地预示着
a welcome end to white colonial rule.
白人殖民者的统治即将结束了
But Ho Chi Minh, still in exile in China,
但胡志明仍在中国流亡
saw the Japanese as alien invaders,
他把日本人也视作外来入侵者
no more welcome than the French.
并没有比法国人好到哪去
They were only interested in exploiting his country
他们只想着剥削他的国家
and seizing Vietnamese crops to fill their own rice bowls.
拿越南人的粮食去填饱自己的肚子
The time had come, he said,
是时候了 他说
to rally "patriots of all ages and all types,
要召集 "所有年龄和所有类型的爱国者
peasants, workers, merchants and soldiers"
农民 工人 商人和士兵"
to defeat the Japanese and the collaborationist French.
来抗击日本人和通德的法国人
In February of 1941,
1941年2月
after three decades away from his homeland,
在离开祖国30年后
Ho Chi Minh slipped back across the Chinese border into Vietnam
胡志明偷偷越过中国边境回到了越南
and set up headquarters near the remote village of Pac Bo
并在偏远的北坡村附近建立了总部
in a limestone cave at the side of a mountain
这个村边的石灰岩山洞总部
he named for Karl Marx,
被他叫做 卡尔·马克思洞
overlooking a jungle stream he named for his hero,
山脚下的丛林溪流也以他的英雄命名
Lenin.
列宁溪
There, he founded a revolutionary movement,
在这里 他成立了一个革命运动组织
which he called the Vietnam Independence League...
他称之为 越南独立同盟
the Viet Minh.
简称 越盟
每个人都想加入越盟参战
大多数人都不知道越盟
陈玉泉
南越陆战队
是一个共产主义组织
To build and lead a fighting force for his revolution,
为了打造和领导一支革命武装力量
Ho called upon Vo Nguyen Giap,
胡志明叫来了武元甲
a one-time teacher of French history
武元甲曾是教法国历史的老师
who had instructed the children of Hanoi's elite.
在河内教导过精英们的孩子
Giap was an early convert to communism,
武元甲很早就接受了共产主义
whose life-long hatred for the French intensified
法国人在监狱里把他的妻子殴打至死
when they beat his wife to death in prison.
这加剧了他终身对法国人的血海深仇
Inspired by Napoleon, Lawrence of Arabia,
在拿破仑和阿拉伯的劳伦斯
and the communist Chinese revolutionary Mao Zedong,
以及中国共产革命者毛泽东的鼓舞下
Giap had already begun to develop a distinctive theory of warfare
武元甲已经开始形成了一种独特的战争理论
that relied on guerrilla tactics
即依靠游击战术
until a full-scale conventional attack could be mounted.
再静等时机发动全面的常规进攻
In the fight for independence which he believed was coming,
他相信在即将到来的独立之战中
his armies, Giap said, would be "everywhere and nowhere."
他的军队将 "无处不在又无影无形"
The reason Vietnamese had always resort to guerrilla warfare
越南人总采取游击战是因为
was because we were a small country.
我们是一个小国家
And it was just a way of fight the weak against the strong.
通过这种方式就能以弱打强
Don't fight unless you're sure you can win,
不打无把握之仗
杨文麦
河内
and surprise is a big element.
出其不意 攻其不备
Choose your own battle.
致人而不致于人
I had about 26 guys that day out of 45.
那天我带了45人中的26人出来
We were always somewhat understrength.
我们总是有点儿寡不敌众
迈克·希尼
陆军
And this day we were quite understrength.
但这天真的是太寡不敌众了
My platoon's on point.
我的排队正在侦察
Go, go, go, go, go!
走 走 走 走 走
And all of a sudden the very point man,
突然之间 最前头的侦察兵
the first guy in the column,
队列中的那第一个人
said, "VC on the trail. VC on the trail."
他说 "路上有越共 路上有越共"
Before I had a chance to digest this...
我还没来得及消化这讯息
... he went down, shot right through the chest.
他就倒下了 胸口正中一枪
And what was a very well-laid ambush erupted.
他们发动了一场精心准备的埋伏
I knew I'd lost a bunch of guys.
我知道自己失去了很多兄弟
I said a prayer to God
我向上帝祷告说
saying,
我说
basically, "If you need any more guys from my platoon,
"如果你需要带走更多我排里的人
take me. Don't take any more of my men."
那就带走我吧 别再带走我的兄弟了"
As soon as I said it,
我一说完这话
I freaked myself out and said,
我都被自己吓到了
"Holy shit. Can I take that prayer back?"
"妈的 我能收回那祷告吗"
By the Spring of 1945,
到1945年春天
more than three years after the Japanese attack on Pearl Harbor,
日本偷袭珍珠港已经过去了3年多
the United States government was looking for allies
美国政府正在寻找
behind the lines in Vietnam.
越南战线上的盟友
The Americans were hoping to find a way
美国人希望能找到方法
to undermine Japanese forces there
来破坏越南的日本军队
when they were contacted by Ho Chi Minh.
这时胡志明联系上了他们
And so it was decided to drop an OSS team in
他们决定投放一支战略情报局队伍
to meet with the Viet Minh leadership.
去跟越盟领导层会面
Paul Hoagland was the medic on the team.
保罗·霍格兰是队里的医生
And the first thing he was told was that
他一到就马上被告知说
唐纳德·格雷格
中情局
he must attend to their leader, who was desperately sick.
他需要去见他们病重的领导
So he was taken to a grass shack
所以他被带到了一个草棚里
where a bewhiskered, skinny man lay on a bundle of straw,
一个瘦弱的长着胡子的人就躺在草堆上
desperately ill.
病得很严重
And that was Ho Chi Minh.
那就是胡志明
The OSS, the secret wartime precursor of the CIA,
战略情报局是中情局的战时前身
supplied Ho's ragtag guerrillas with arms
他们给胡志明的破烂游击队提供了武器
and marveled at how quickly they learned to handle them.
并惊讶于他们很快地就学会如何使用了
Ho Chi Minh began to call his followers
胡志明开始把自己的追随者们称作
the "Viet-American Army,"
"越美联军"
and praised the United States as a "champion of democracy"
并赞扬美国是 "民主的捍卫者"
that would surely help them end colonial rule.
且肯定能帮他们结束殖民统治
我们看到美国人来了
当我们看到美国人时
裴琰
南越外交官
我们把他们看作自由人
来解放人们
他们已经解放过欧洲了
Meanwhile, famine gripped the northern part of the country.
同时饥荒席卷着这个国家的北部
Hundreds of thousands of Vietnamese were dying of starvation
数十万越南人都快被饿死了
while Japanese storehouses were filled with rice.
而日本人的仓库都还满是粮食
In those days, garbage was collected by people pushing carts.
那时期里 人们都推着车来收集垃圾
And my mother remembers that every morning
我母亲还记得每天早上
she would see these garbage carts going around
她就会看到这些垃圾车出来街上
and people picking up dead bodies and throwing them on the cart.
人们就会把尸体捡起来扔到车上
It was incredible.
那简直难以置信
And people who lived through it never, never forgot.
经历了这一切的人永远也不会忘记
Duong Van Mai's father was the deputy governor of a province east of Hanoi,
杨文麦的父亲是河内东部某省的副总督
the son and grandson of mandarins who had all served the French.
他祖上两代都是为法国人效劳的官吏
He and his wife had 17 children.
他跟夫人共育有17名儿女
Parents who had children who were, you know, plump,
有着许多小孩的父母们
were very afraid of their children being stolen and killed.
都很担心自己的孩子会被偷走或杀死
And it was really like hell on earth.
那就像是人间地狱
The government didn't have a clue on how to deal with this calamity.
政府不知道要怎么应对这场灾难
But Ho Chi Minh did.
但胡志明知道
He directed the Viet Minh to break
他下令越盟尽可能地
into the Japanese storehouses wherever they could
闯进日本人的仓库
and distribute the rice to the people.
把库存的粮食发给民众
They were hailed as saviors.
他们被誉为救世主
1945年8月6日
When an atomic bomb destroyed Hiroshima,
后来一颗原子弹摧毁了广岛
and three days later a second one destroyed Nagasaki,
3天后另一颗原子弹摧毁了长崎
Japanese surrender seemed imminent.
日本人似乎马上就要投降了
Ho Chi Minh called upon all Vietnamese to rise up
胡志明号召所有越南人奋起
and take over their own country
接管他们自己的国家
before the Free French could reestablish
免得自由法国会重建起
their old colonial regime.
原有的殖民统治
They did, in cities and towns across the country.
越南人夺回了全国各地的城镇
On September 2, 1945,
1945年9月2日
the same day the Japanese formally surrendered,
这天日本正式投降了
hundreds of thousands of Vietnamese streamed into Ba Dinh Square in Hanoi
成千上万的越南人涌入河内的巴亭广场
to see for the first time the mysterious leader of the Viet Minh
首次见到了神秘的越盟领导人
and hear him proclaim Vietnam's independence.
并听着他宣布越南独立了
With an OSS officer standing nearby,
有名战略情报局的官员也站在附近
Ho Chi Minh began with the words of Thomas Jefferson:
胡志明以托马斯·杰斐逊的名言开场
"All men are created equal.
"人生而平等
They are endowed by their creator with certain unalienable rights;
造物主赋予他们若干不可剥夺的权利
that among these are life, liberty
其中包括生命权 自由权
and the pursuit of happiness."
以及追求幸福的权利"
所有的越南人 不只是我
都觉得从今往后越南都将独立
童士元
越盟
自由 统一 领土完整
在世界地图上也有正式的名字
每个人都很自豪
Ho Chi Minh had great hopes
胡志明很期待
that the U.S. would support the Vietnam desire for independence,
美国会支持越南的独立愿望
乔治·威克斯
战略情报局
not necessarily by intervening
不一定需要直接干预
but by doing what it could
但美国可以尽可能地
to support an independence movement.
支持他们的独立运动
Ho Chi Minh's hopes for American support were calculated
胡志明指望美国的支持固然有自己的算盘
but understandable.
但也无可厚非
President Franklin Roosevelt had promised a postwar world
罗斯福总统曾允诺过战后的世界
that would "respect the rights of all peoples
将会 "尊重所有民族选择
to choose the form of government under which they live."
其生活所处的政府形式的权利"
But Roosevelt was dead now,
但罗斯福现已离世
and his successor, Harry Truman,
他的继任者哈里·杜鲁门
had inherited a very different world.
所接手的是一个很不一样的世界
The alliance with the Soviet Union that had
昔日打赢了二战的
won the Second World War had collapsed.
美苏同盟如今已然解体
The Soviets now occupied the
苏联现在侵占吞并了
Eastern European countries they had overrun,
一堆的东欧国家
and hoped to spread their influence farther,
并想将其影响力进一步
into Iran, Turkey, and the Mediterranean.
扩散到伊朗 土耳其和地中海
A new cold war had begun.
一场新的冷战开始了
French president Charles De Gaulle warned
法国总统戴高乐警告说
that if the United States insisted
如果美国坚持要让
on independence for her colonies,
法属殖民地独立的话
France might have no choice
法国可能会别无选择
but to "fall into the Russian orbit."
只能 "成为俄国的卫星国"
The United States must do nothing to undercut
美国必须不能削弱阻碍
the restoration of France's empire,
法兰西帝国的恢复壮大
including Vietnam.
当然也不能动到越南
西贡
There were hardly any Americans in Vietnam, you know...
在越南的美国人极少
State Department people,
只有国务院人员
consular officials,
领事馆官员
a few businessmen.
以及几个商人
Hardly anyone from this country
几乎没有美国人
乔治·威克斯
战略情报局
knew where Vietnam was located.
会知道越南在哪里
George Wickes was part of a seven-man OSS mission
乔治·威克斯隶属战略情报局的一个七人小队
sent to Saigon, the largest city in the south.
他们被派到西贡 这是南边最大的城市
The United States was officially neutral,
美国在官方上保持中立
hoping the French and Viet Minh could reach
希望法国和越盟能够
some peaceful solution on their own.
自行达成某种和解
Allied leaders had agreed temporarily to divide Vietnam
盟国领导们同意暂时将越南
into two separate zones.
分成两个独立的区域
Nationalist Chinese troops were to handle things in the north.
由中国国民党军接管北越的事务
British colonial troops would try to perform the same task in the south,
英国殖民军也将在南越执行同样的任务
where rival factions, including the French and Viet Minh,
但南越的敌对双方 法国和越盟
were already fighting in the streets of Saigon.
已经在西贡的街头打了起来
No one was in charge.
没有人能掌管大局
On both sides, there was brutality and atrocity and violence.
双方都是野蛮残暴
It wasn't quite a civil war
那不能算是一场内战
but it was getting very close to civil war in the streets of Saigon.
但在西贡街头越来越像是一场内战了
Lieutenant Colonel Peter Dewey, the 28-year-old
28岁的中校彼得·杜威
commander of the OSS in Saigon,
是战略情报局在西贡的指挥官
tried to make sense of it all.
他想要理清这一切
Right from the start he was in touch with everybody...
从一开始他就跟各方接触
not only the French,
不只是法国人
but very soon he established a connection with
他还很快联系上了
various Vietnamese groups.
越南的各种团体
The Viet Minh soon established themselves
越盟很快就主动地成为了
as the most successful.
联系最为密切的
Dewey, who spoke fluent French,
杜威讲着流利的法语
brokered talks between a Viet Minh spokesman
斡旋于越盟的一名发言人
and the senior French representative in the city.
与城里的一名法国高级代表之间
His efforts infuriated British general Douglas Gracey,
他的努力激怒了英国将军道格拉斯·格雷西
who commanded Allied forces in the south.
将军指挥着南边的盟国军队
Gracey was convinced that French control
格雷西相信应该
should be reimposed as soon as possible.
尽快恢复法国的控制
By conferring with the Viet Minh, Gracey said,
格雷西说正在和越盟谈判的
Colonel Dewey had become a "subversive" force.
杜威中校已经成了一个 "颠覆" 分子
The violence in and around Saigon escalated.
西贡内外的暴力冲突变本加厉
Colonel Dewey urgently cabled his superiors:
杜威中校急忙发电讯给上级
Vietnam "is burning," he wrote.
他写道 越南 "正在熊熊燃烧"
"The French and British are finished here
"法国人和英国人在这里已经没戏了"
and the United States," he concluded, "ought to clear out of Southeast Asia."
他总结道 "美国也该离开东南亚了"
Two days later,
两天之后
September 26, 1945,
1945年9月26日
he set out for the airport,
他出发前往机场
prepared to fly to OSS headquarters.
准备飞回战略情报局的总部
At a roadblock,
在一处路障前
the Viet Minh mistook Dewey for a Frenchman
越盟把杜威误认作法国人
and opened fire.
并开枪射击了
He was killed instantly.
他当场身亡
Ho Chi Minh wrote to the United States
胡志明写信给美国
lamenting the death of Dewey,
向杜威之死表示哀悼
whom he recognized
他认可杜威
as a person sympathetic to his cause.
是一位同情他事业的人
It seemed a terrible irony that Dewey, who was
这对杜威来说似乎是个天大的讽刺
doing what he could to help the Vietnamese independence movement
他尽己所能地帮助越南的独立运动
should have been killed by the Vietnamese by a mistake.
最后却阴差阳错地死在越南人手上
An elderly African-American woman answered the door.
一名非裔的美国老妇人来开门了
文森特·冈本
陆军
I think she knew the instant she saw us why we were there.
我想她一看到我们在那里就知道怎么回事了
And the padre said, uh,
军队的牧师跟她说
"I'm... I'm terribly sorry to inform you,
"我非常抱歉地通知您
but your son was killed in Vietnam."
您的儿子在越南阵亡了"
And she just sat down. Didn't say a word.
她就只是坐了下来 一句话都没说
Then the... her husband says, "No, there's a mistake."
然后她的丈夫说 "不对 这肯定是弄错了"
He comes back with this letter.
他回去拿了这封信出来
And he said, "Look, see?
他说 "看这 看到了吧
We got it yesterday, my... our son was still alive yesterday."
昨天才收到的信 我们儿子昨天都还活着"
And the chaplain looked at the letter
牧师看了下那封信
and he said, "It's a week old.
他说 "这是一周之前的了
I think your son was killed on the day he wrote this letter."
我想您的儿子应该是在写信的同一天阵亡的"
In the fall of 1945,
1945年秋天
a week after Colonel Dewey's death,
杜威中校死后一周
fresh French troops began arriving in Saigon,
新补充进来的法军抵达了西贡
taking over from the British.
接替了原先的英国人
They quickly established control of the city
他们迅速控制住了这座城市
and set out to reoccupy the entire country.
并出发去重新占领整个国家
Ho Chi Minh hoped somehow to achieve independence
胡志明希望能找到某种方式既可实现独立
without a war with France,
又不用跟法国开战
and he still hoped the United States would intervene.
他仍然希望美国能进行干涉
"You never had an empire,
"我们永远不会成为一个帝国
never exploited the Asian peoples,"
永远不会剥削亚洲人民"
he would tell a visiting American journalist.
他向到访的一名美国记者说道
"Do not be blinded by this issue of communism."
"不要被共产主义这个问题蒙蔽了双眼"
He did not want to fight the French as an enemy of America.
他不想把法国立成美国的敌人来打
And, in fact, I saw the letters he wrote to President Truman
事实上 我看了他写给杜鲁门总统的信
莱斯利·吉尔伯
国防部
saying, "We believe in the same things you believe."
他说 "我们所相信的正是你们所相信的"
Those letters I saw in the CIA files,
我在中情局档案里看到的这些信
they had never been given to President Truman.
它们都未曾转交给过杜鲁门总统
In June of 1946,
1946年6月
Ho Chi Minh returned to Paris
胡志明回到巴黎
in a fruitless attempt to get the French
徒劳地想要法国人
to live up to a promise they had made
兑现他们的承诺
of increased autonomy for his country.
提高越南的自主权
While Ho was away,
胡志明不在时
General Giap began consolidating
武元甲将军开始巩固起
communist control of the revolution.
共产党对革命的控制了
He conducted a merciless purge of
他残酷地清洗了
members of rival nationalist parties
民族主义对手政党的成员
and people he called "reactionary saboteurs"...
还有那些他所谓的 "反动破坏分子"
landlords and moneylenders,
地主和高利贷主
Trotskyites and Catholics,
托洛茨基派和天主教徒
men and women accused of collaborating with the French.
还有被控叛通法国的男男女女
Hundreds were shot, drowned, buried alive.
上百人被枪杀 淹死和活埋
我看到越盟杀死了自己的越南同胞
他们不是真的为越南人而战
林光世
南越军队
他们只为国际共产体系而战
On December 19, 1946,
1946年12月19日
after months of building tension,
经过数月的紧张加剧后
fighting broke out in Hanoi between the Viet Minh and the French.
越盟和法国在河内爆发了战斗
The Viet Minh proved no match for French firepower.
最终越盟的火力不敌法国
Ho, Giap, and their comrades slipped out of the city
胡志明和武元甲及其同志们跑到了城外
and returned to their mountain stronghold far to the north.
回到了他们远在北边的山间要塞
"Those who have rifles will use their rifles,"
"有枪的人会拿起他们的枪"
Ho declared in a radio address
胡志明在广播里号召
calling for a nationwide guerrilla war.
发动全国范围的游击战
"Those who have swords will use swords;
"有剑的人会拿起他们的剑
those who have no swords will use spades or sticks."
没有剑的人会拿起铁铲和木棍"
我们有种强烈的责任感要去为国家而战
在我的记忆里那是一段开心美好的时光
我们在前去战斗时还都唱着歌
阮玉
越盟
那些很浪漫的歌
But the country Ho Chi Minh hoped to unite
但是胡志明想要团结起来的这个国家
was itself bitterly divided.
本身已经四分五裂了
Families were being torn apart.
就连家庭也被撕裂了
Despite her father's position in the French government,
尽管父亲供职于法国政府
Duong Van Mai's sister felt compelled to answer Ho's call.
杨文麦的姐姐仍觉得必须要回应胡志明的号召
My older sister Thang was married to a man
我的姐姐棠嫁给了一个
who had great sympathy for the Viet Minh.
十分同情越盟的人
And by that time Ho Chi Minh had evacuated
那时胡志明已经把他的政府
his government to the mountain base.
转移到了山间的基地里
So my sister and her husband trekked
所以我的姐姐和姐夫就一路
all the way from Hanoi toward the base
从河内跋涉到那个基地
in order to join the resistance against the French.
以求加入反抗法国的队伍
So the Vietnam War was really a civil war
所以越战在家庭层面上
down to the family level.
确实是一场内战
法国在印度支那推进!
France poured thousands of men into Vietnam...
法国派遣了成千上万人到越南
French regulars, European mercenaries,
法国常规军 欧洲雇佣军
and colonial troops from Morocco, Algeria, Tunisia, and Senegal...
还有摩洛哥 阿尔及利亚 突尼斯和塞内加尔的殖民地军队
who fought alongside an army of Cambodians,
协同作战的还有缅甸军队
Laotians,
老挝军队
and anti-communist Vietnamese.
以及反共的越南人
French forces managed to occupy
法国军队设法占领了
most of the large towns and province capitals
多数的大城镇和省会
and established hundreds of isolated outposts.
并建造了成百上千的独立前哨
The French also set out to try to win over rural Vietnamese
法国还准备争取来越南的农民
through a program they called pacification...
他们为此开展了一项 "平息" 行动
平息
pacification...
安抚和解之意
building dikes, schools and roads,
他们修建堤坝 学校和道路
and vaccinating children.
给孩童接种疫苗
The French would pacify a village
法国人安抚了一座村子后
and during the daytime they could control it.
他们在白天能控制这村子
But at night the Viet Minh would come back.
但到晚上越盟就又回来了
And so it was never completely secure.
所以永远不会有绝对的安全
My father would shake his head and said, you know,
我父亲就摇头说道
"Pacification is really futile
"平息行动真的是徒劳
because it's like trying to hold sand in your fingers."
因为这就像是要用手指去握住流沙"
The Viet Minh mined roads,
越盟破坏道路
blew up bridges and railroads,
炸毁桥梁和铁路
ambushed French patrols,
伏击法国的巡逻队
and then disappeared.
然后消失无踪
French soldiers sometimes took revenge on the nearest village,
法国士兵有时会报复最近的村庄
burning homes, raping women,
火烧房屋 奸淫妇女
executing men suspected of aiding the Viet Minh.
处死有帮助越盟嫌疑的男人
1948年 在我的家乡
法国人开着坦克进来
烧了我们的房屋
我们用来犁田的水牛
很多都被他们开枪打死了
那时我还是个小孩
我看见了那一幕
那场景就烙印在我的记忆里
黎公训
越盟
But the communists proved
但是共产党的残暴
every bit as ruthless as the French.
也跟法国人不相上下
"It is better to kill even those who might be innocent,"
"宁可错杀无辜"
one commander said, "than to let a guilty person go."
有名同志如此说道 "不可放过一个"
And they specifically targeted
他们尤其针对那些
anyone who had links to the French.
跟法国有所联系的人
Once my father started working for the French,
我父亲一旦开始为法国工作
then he was a target,
他马上就成了目标
especially the higher he rose,
尤其他官越做越大
the bigger target he became.
他这靶子就愈发明显
A Viet Minh agent actually came in with a pistol
有名越盟特工真的带了把手枪进来
to shoot him
准备开枪打他
but at the last moment decided not to.
不过他在最后一刻放弃了
我看到越盟
逮捕了效力法国军队的越南士兵
把他们脱光
陈乐辉
南越军队
然后残酷地杀死他们
把他们活活烧死
他们不想浪费子弹在这些人身上
我们生活在两方压迫者之下
French casualties continued to mount.
法国人的伤亡数量持续上升
"There are days when we are so discouraged
"有些时候我们十分沮丧
that we would like to give it all up,"
我们甚至都想放弃算了"
a French soldier wrote his mother.
一名法国士兵写信给母亲如此说道
"Convoys under attack,
"我们的车队被伏击
roads cut,
道路被阻断
firing in all directions every night,
每晚都要向四面八方开火
the indifference at home."
国内对此漠不关心"
While I was there I had the opportunity to call my mother.
我在那里的时候 有时能打电话给我妈
And I was telling my mother what was happening over there,
我跟我妈说那里发生了什么
and I was telling her how
我跟她说
she shouldn't believe what she sees in the newspaper and sees on television
不要相信新闻和电视上说的
because we're losing the war.
因为我们正在输掉这场战争
I said, "And you'll probably never see me again
我说 "你可能再也见不到我了
because we're the most northern outpost
因为我们是陆战队里
罗杰·哈里斯
陆战队
that the Marines have, you know."
最北边的哨点"
We could literally... could look right into North Vietnam.
我们一探头就能看到北越了
We could see the sparks when the guns fired on us.
我们能看到对方枪口的焰火
And I said, "And everybody in my unit is dying.
我说 "我队里的每个人都要死了
I probably won't be coming back."
我可能回不去了"
And my mother said, "No, you're coming back."
我妈就说 "不会的 你会回来的"
She said, "I talk to God every day and you're special.
她说 "我每天都跟上帝祷告 你跟别人不一样
You're coming back."
你会回来的"
And I said, "Ma, everybody's mother
我说 "妈 每个妈妈都会觉得
thinks that they're special.
自己的小孩是特例
You know, I'm putting pieces of special people in bags."
我就在把一些特例的遗骸装进尸体袋里"
1949年8月29日
President Truman's dramatic announcement
杜鲁门总统惊人地宣布说
that Russia had the atom secret
俄国秘密拥有了原子弹
caused state departments all over the world to stir uneasily.
这引起了世界各国国务院的不安
We were very aware that there was a Cold War
我们很清楚地意识到这是场冷战
and that we had an enemy,
我们面对着一个敌人
and that enemy was the Soviet Union.
这敌人就是苏联
The United States stood at one pole
美国站在一个极点
哈尔·库什纳
弗吉尼亚州 丹维尔市
and the Soviet Union stood at the other pole.
苏联站在另一极点
It was kind of a Manichean dynamic
那就像是摩尼教里的动态平衡一样
that there was evil and there was good.
世界上既有恶 也有善
And we were good, and the other side was evil.
我们是善的一方 另一方则是恶的
It wasn't morally ambiguous.
双方泾渭分明
Just a few weeks after Russia became a nuclear power,
俄国成为有核力量才几星期
there was more stunning news...
骇人的消息还将持续传来
communist forces under Mao Zedong seized control of China.
毛泽东领导的共产力量控制了中国
Separate communist insurrections were also underway
互相独立的共产叛乱也席卷了
in the British colonies of Burma and Malaya.
英国的缅甸和马来亚殖民地
In January 1950,
1950年1月
Mao formally recognized Ho Chi Minh's insurgency
毛泽东正式承认胡志明的叛乱力量
and agreed to provide the arms, equipment,
并同意提供胡志明所寻求的
and military training he had been seeking.
武器装备和军事训练援助
The Soviets recognized the Viet Minh as well,
苏联也承认了越盟政权
and also offered help.
并也提供援助
President Truman, who was being blamed
杜鲁门总统被政治对手
by his political opponents for having "lost" China,
指责说他 "丢掉" 了中国
and having failed to "contain" communism,
而且没能 "遏制" 共产主义
approved a $23 million aid program
现在他批准了一项2300万美元的援助项目
for the French in Vietnam.
用来帮助越南的法军
The United States was no longer neutral.
美国不再中立了
We were caught on the horns of a dilemma
我们陷入了一种困境里
of how can we maintain our friendship and our alliance with the French
我们怎么能维持跟法国的友谊和同盟
山姆·威尔逊
陆军
and support them in Indochina
并在印度支那支持他们
while we, as a former colony ourselves,
同时作为前殖民地的我们
sympathized with the Vietnamese and their aspirations
还能同情越南人
for freedom and independence?
对自由和独立追求?
A highly trained and well-equipped North Korean Army
一支训练有素 装备精良的北韩军队
swarmed across the 38th parallel to attack
越过三八线来攻击了
unprepared South Korean defenders.
措手不及的南韩守军
In June of 1950,
1950年7月
China's ally, communist North Korea,
中国的盟友 共产主义北韩
invaded South Korea.
入侵了南韩
President Truman ordered tens of thousands of
杜鲁门总统指挥数十万的
American ground troops onto the Korean Peninsula.
美国地面部队进入了朝鲜半岛
The United States and its allies
美国及其盟友
eventually pushed the invaders back north.
最终把入侵者赶回了北边
Meanwhile in southern China,
同时在中国南方
Mao's military was beginning to turn the Viet Minh
毛泽东的军队正开始把越盟
into a modern fighting force,
改造成一支现代战斗部队
capable of inflicting a heavy toll on the French occupiers.
让他们有能力重创法国占领军
In July, the Truman administration
杜鲁门政府在7月份
quietly dispatched transport planes
悄悄地派出了数架运输机
and a shipload of jeeps to Vietnam.
以及一船的吉普车到越南
Thirty-five military advisors
还有35名军事顾问随行
went along to oversee their use.
来监管这些物资的使用
None of them, and no one in the American embassy,
这些顾问和美国大使馆里的所有人
spoke a word of Vietnamese.
都不会讲越南语
But the United States was now officially in Vietnam.
但现在美国正式介入了越南
In October of 1950,
1950年10月
hundreds of thousands of Chinese troops
成千上万的中国军队
began pouring into North Korea,
开始涌入北韩
driving the allies back down the peninsula.
并把盟军赶回了半岛后方
As that fighting raged,
半岛激战之时
Truman continued to increase military aid
杜鲁门继续增加军事援助
for the French war in Vietnam.
支持在越南的法军
If aggression is successful in Korea,
如果他们成功入侵了韩国
we can expect it to spread throughout Asia and Europe
那我们就等着赤潮传遍亚洲和欧洲
and to this hemisphere.
传到我们这个半球吧
We are fighting in Korea
我们在韩国打的仗
for our own national security and survival.
乃是为了我们国家的安全与生存
In the autumn of 1951,
1951年秋天
a young Massachusetts congressman
一名年轻的马萨诸塞州议员
named John F. Kennedy
约翰·肯尼迪
dined at the rooftop bar of the Hotel Majestic
在马杰斯酒店的顶楼餐吧里一边吃着晚饭
overlooking Saigon.
一边俯瞰着西贡
As he and his party ate,
他和党员们一边吃着
they could hear the thunder of guns across the Saigon River.
一边听着枪声从西贡河对面传来
French commanders assured Kennedy
法军指挥官向肯尼迪保证
that with more American support,
只要美国提供更多的援助
French rule would be re-established.
法国就能在这里恢复统治
But Kennedy spent two hours with Seymour Topping,
但肯尼迪和西默·托平待了两个小时
a seasoned American reporter,
后者是经验丰富的美国记者
who gave him a very different perspective:
他向肯尼迪讲了另一番故事
the French were losing, he said,
他说 法国正在失败
and many Vietnamese, who had once admired the Americans,
而且许多曾经敬仰美国人的越南人
were beginning to despise them for backing the French.
也开始鄙视他们对法国的支持了
Kennedy believed the reporter.
肯尼迪相信了记者的说法
Unless the United States could persuade the Vietnamese
除非美国能够让越南人相信
that it was as opposed to "injustice and inequality"
这就像是对抗共产主义那样
as it was to communism,
在对抗 "不平等与不公正"
he told his constituents when he got home,
他回国后跟选民说
the current effort would result in "foredoomed failure."
目前的这些付出只能换来 "注定的失败"
In 1952,
1952年
General Dwight Eisenhower was elected president,
德怀特·艾森豪威尔将军当选总统
in part because he promised
一方面是因为他承诺
to take a tougher stance on communism.
会更加强硬地对待共产主义
That year, American taxpayers
同年 美国的纳税者
were footing more than 30% of the bill
负担了法国在越南
for the French war in Vietnam.
30%多的军费
Within two years,
在两年内
that number would rise to nearly 80%.
这一数字变上升到了近80%
And many of you ask this question:
你们中的很多人都问到说
Why is the United States spending hundreds of millions of dollars
为什么美国要花费数百亿美元
supporting the forces of the French Union
去支持法兰西联邦的军队
in the fight against communism in Indochina?
在印度支那抗击共产主义?
I think perhaps if we go over to the map here,
我想只要我们看一下这边的地图
I can indicate to you why it is so vitally important.
你们就会知道它为什么那么重要了
Here's Indochina.
这里是印度支那
理查德·尼克松
副总统
If Indochina falls,
如果印度支那沦陷了
Thailand is put in almost impossible position.
泰国也将难以为继
The same is true of Malaya with its rubber and tin.
富产橡胶和锡的马来亚也将一样
Now may I say that as far as the war in Indochina is concerned,
就印度支那的战争而言
that I was there, right on the battlefield, or close to it,
我曾经到过那战场 或者也接近过那战地
and it's a bloody war, and it's a bitter one.
它确实是一场血腥而艰苦的战争
By 1953, the French had been fighting for seven years.
到1953年 法国人已经打了7年了
They had suffered over 100,000 casualties
他们付出了10万多人的伤亡
and failed to pacify the countryside.
也没能平息越南乡间
Six commanders had come and gone.
六任指挥官来了又走
Nevertheless, the seventh commander,
但是第七任司令官
General Henri Navarre, assured his countrymen
亨利·纳瓦尔将军仍向法国国民
that victory was near.
保证胜利在望
"Now we can see it clearly," he said,
他说 "现在我们看到局势明了"
"like the light at the end of the tunnel."
"就像是隧道尽头的光明一样"
Meanwhile, large parts of the French population
同时很多的法国民众
were horrified by reports of French brutality
都震惊于报道上所说的法军暴行
and the widespread use of napalm...
以及凝固汽油弹的大范围使用
gelatinized petroleum
这种凝固汽油
that burned foliage,
被用来焚烧丛林
homes,
村庄
and human flesh.
以及人体肤肉
When returning French troops disembarked at Marseilles,
当归国的法军士兵在马赛下船时
members of the longshoremen's union pelted them with rocks.
码头工会的成员们朝他们扔石头
Parisian leftists began to call the conflict
巴黎左派人士们开始称这场冲突为
"La Sale Guerre"... "The Dirty War."
"肮脏的战争"
The camera was a close-up,
那是一个特写镜头
was over the shoulder of this storm trooper
拍到了一名警卫人员的肩膀
罗恩·弗里兹
陆军
who had a kid by the scruff of his shirt and
有个孩子抓着他的领口
he smacks him.
他就把他砸倒在地
People screaming...
人们在尖叫...
At that moment in time,
在那个时候
I realized that anybody who really cared for America
我意识到真正关心美国的人
was sent halfway around the world
都已经被送到地球的另一端
chasing some ghost in a jungle.
在丛林里追逐着一些牛鬼蛇神
In the meantime, my country's being torn apart.
同时我的国家被撕裂成两半了
So I saw somebody who looked like my dad
所以我才会看到一个跟我爸一样的人
hitting somebody who looked like me.
殴打着一个跟我一样的人
Whose side would I be on?
我该站那一队呢
In Korea, three years of combat end
在韩国的三年战事结束了
as United Nations and communist negotiators at Panmunjom sign a truce.
联合国与共产代表在板门店签约停战
In July of 1953,
1953年7月
the Korean War ended in a negotiated settlement
韩战以谈判解决而结束
and a still-divided peninsula.
留下了一个仍然分裂的半岛
American policymakers saw it as proof
美国的决策者认为这就证明了
that communism in Asia could be contained.
亚洲的共产主义是可以遏制的
That fall, the French indicated their willingness
那年秋天 法国人表示他们愿意
to begin talks to end the fighting in Vietnam.
开启谈判以结束越南战事
Ho Chi Minh agreed to meet.
胡志明同意了会面
But before the negotiators were to convene in Geneva,
但在谈判代表齐聚日内瓦之前
each side sought to improve its position on the battlefield.
双方都想在战场上改善己方的局势
General Navarre set up a fortified base
纳瓦尔将军在越南西北部的
in a remote valley in northwestern Vietnam
偏远山谷里设立了森严的基地
called Dien Bien Phu,
这就是奠边府
where he hoped to lure the Viet Minh
他想把越盟引诱到这里
into a decisive battle.
进行一场决定性战役
Navarre was certain that superior French firepower and air support
纳瓦尔相信法军的优势火力和空中支持
would crush any attack by the Viet Minh.
将碾碎越盟的一切进攻
He and his commanders saw no need to worry about
他和手下的军官们觉得不用担心
the jungle-covered hills that overlooked his 11,000 men,
两边满是丛林的山丘俯瞰着他那
dug in on the valley floor.
在谷底挖坑道的1.1万人
The artillery commander was so confident of victory,
炮兵司令官信心满满
he complained, "I have more guns than I need."
他抱怨说 "我都用不到这么多火炮"
General Giap saw his chance.
武元甲将军看到了可乘之机
"We decided to wipe out at all costs
他回忆道 "我们决定不惜一切代价
the whole enemy force at Dien Bien Phu," he remembered.
肃清在奠边府的所有敌人"
To do it, he pulled off one of the greatest
为此他发动了军事史上
logistical feats in military history...
最大的一次后勤运动
a feat that would be restaged in propaganda films
这次壮举在数十年里将会不断地
and celebrated for decades.
被搬上银幕 被人们庆祝
A quarter of a million civilian porters...
25万名平民搬运工
nearly half of them women...
其中近一半为女性
moved everything he needed for a siege,
他们搬运着他所需的一切围困物资
from sacks of rice
从装米的麻袋
to disassembled artillery pieces,
到火炮的零部件
on foot through the jungle.
都被他们在丛林里徒步搬着
Giap surrounded the valley with 50,000 soldiers
武将军用5万名士兵围住山谷
and 200 big guns,
还有200门大炮
dug-in and camouflaged so well
也都掩藏得很好
they could not be spotted from the air.
从空中也不会被发现
On March 13, 1954,
1954年3月13日
Viet Minh artillery on the hillsides
山坡上的越盟火炮
began raining down 50 shells a minute
开始每分钟倾泻下50发炮弹
on the French troops huddled below.
炸在法军密密麻麻的山谷里
The airstrip was destroyed.
飞机跑道都被摧毁了
The besieged troops could only be reinforced
被困的法军只能通过空投来
and resupplied by airdrop.
补给兵力和物资
The French artillery commander, who had underestimated his enemy,
低估了敌军的法国炮兵司令
committed suicide.
自杀身亡
The airlift to Dien Bien Phu continues...
对奠边府的空中补给持续着...
vital men and supplies for the heroic garrison
重要的人员和物资补给帮助了英勇的驻军
that has defied the massed Viet Minh onslaughts for over six weeks.
抵抗了越盟6个星期多的猛攻
Today, Dien Bien Phu is a human dam
今天的奠边府就像是一座人类堤坝
trying to stem the red tide
努力地阻挡着赤潮
that threatens to engulf Southeast Asia.
淹没整个东南亚
The French government begged
法国政府请求
President Eisenhower to intervene.
艾森豪威尔总统进行干预
He refused to act
总统拒绝行动
without Congressional approval and support from European allies.
因为没有国会的批准和欧洲盟友的支持
Britain said no
英国表示反对
and the Congress would not support unilateral action.
国会也不会支持单方面的行动
The communists under Ho Chi Minh are able to
胡志明领导的共产力量将会
claim that they are fighting for independence
获得他们所争取的独立
and the French appear to be fighting for a maintain...
而法国的战斗则是为了维持...
maintenance of colonial rule.
维持殖民统治
I therefore believe that
因此我认为
before the United States moves in, in any degree,
在美国进行任何程度地介入之前
that independence must be granted to the people,
那些人民应当获得独立
that the people must support the struggle.
他们也理应支持这场斗争
"I am convinced," Eisenhower confided to his diary,
艾森豪威尔在日记里坦诚道 "我认为
"that no military victory is possible in this theater."
这件事已经没有军事胜利的可能了"
Still, without consulting Congress,
但是在未咨询国会的情况下
the president had secretly sent more American transport planes,
总统仍秘密地派出了更多的美国运输机
their markings painted over and flown by civilian contractors,
这些飞机修改了涂装并由民间承包商驾驶
to help resupply the desperate French troops at Dien Bien Phu.
用以补给在奠边府的绝望法军
Everyone understood that in and of itself,
大家都明白 就本身而言
Vietnam didn't mean very much.
越南并没那么重要
But they believed, I believed,
但他们相信 我也相信
莱斯利·吉尔伯
国防部
if we lost it,
如果我们丢掉了越南
that the rest of Asia would tumble to communism.
亚洲剩余的部分就将会倒向共产主义
You have broader considerations that might follow
更全面的考虑应遵循
what you would call the falling domino principle.
所谓的多米诺骨牌理论
You have a row of dominoes set up,
现在有着一连串的多米诺骨牌
and you knock over the first one,
你推倒了第一块牌
and what will happen to the last one is the certainty
那么最后一块牌肯定
that it will go over very quickly.
也会很快地倾倒
On the afternoon of May 7, 1954,
1954年5月7日下午
after 55 days of siege,
在被困了55天后
the exhausted French forces at Dien Bien Phu surrendered.
奠边府幸存的法军投降了
They had lost 8,000 men, killed, wounded, or missing.
他们损失了8000人 包括阵亡 负伤和失踪的
General Giap had lost three times as many,
武将军付出了3倍的伤亡代价
but he had won a great victory.
但他取得了一场大胜
奠边府的胜利解放了我们半个国家
我们消灭了一整支法国军队
这次胜利让我们更自信了
阮泰鹏
越盟
Even Duong Van Mai's parents could not help but be impressed.
这令杨文麦的父母也震惊不已
They were very proud that the Viet Minh had defeated
他们也很自豪于越盟能够打败
the French, this great Western power.
法国这一西方强国
Admiration and respect on the one hand,
一方面是钦佩和敬重
but fear on the other hand.
另一方面则是恐惧
And fear was the stronger emotion.
而恐惧占据了上风
"We have been caught bluffing by our enemies,"
"我们装逼不成反被打脸"
Senate Minority Leader Lyndon Johnson said.
参议院少数党领袖林登·约翰逊如此说道
"Today it is Indochina, tomorrow Asia may be in flames.
"今天印度支那沦陷了 明天亚洲可能就陷入战火
And the day after, the Western Alliance will lie in ruins."
后天西方盟国就成为废墟了"
We should have seen it as the end of
我们应该把它看作是殖民时代
the colonial era in Southeast Asia,
在东南亚的终结
which it really was.
事实也是如此
But instead we saw it in Cold War terms,
但我们反而将之视为冷战时期
and we saw it as a defeat for the free world
我们把它看作是自由世界的失败
唐纳德·格雷格
中情局
that was related to the rise of China.
把它跟中国崛起联系到一起
And it was a total misreading of a pivotal event,
这完全是一次对重大事件的误解
which cost us very dearly.
也让我们付出了沉重的代价
The former home of the League of Nations, Geneva, Switzerland,
在国联的前总部 瑞士日内瓦
where East is meeting West in the international conference
东西方将举行国际会议
that may decisively affect the political future of Asia.
并可能决定亚洲的未来政治
The day after the fall of Dien Bien Phu,
奠边府战事结束之后
diplomats from nine nations gathered in Geneva
九个国家的外交官们齐聚日内瓦
to settle the future of Vietnam.
以解决越南的未来
The talks dragged on for nearly two-and-a-half months.
谈判持续了近2个半月
Despite their victory,
虽然取得了胜利
Ho Chi Minh and General Giap could not keep fighting
但胡志明和武元甲仍需要中国
without more support from China and the Soviet Union.
和苏联的更多支持才能继续作战
But China had lost a million men in Korea
但中国已经在朝鲜损失了百万兵力
and did not want to become involved in another war
他们不想再卷进边境上的
along its border.
另一场战争
The Soviet Union was hoping to ease tensions with the West.
苏联也正想跟西方缓和一下关系
Both of Ho Chi Minh's communist patrons
胡志明的两大共产东家
urged him to agree to a negotiated settlement,
都催他同意谈判解决
a partition like the one that had ended the Korean War.
接受跟结束韩战一样的分区治理
Ho had no option but to give in.
胡志明别无选择 只能屈服
In the end, no one was satisfied.
最后没人能满意而归
Vietnam was temporarily to be divided at the 17th parallel.
越南暂时以北纬17°线一分为二
The 130,000 French-led troops stationed in the North
北边法国所领导的13万军队
were to withdraw to the South,
将会撤回到南边
and somewhere between 50,000 and 90,000 Viet Minh
大概5万到9万名越盟士兵
were to "re-group" to the North.
也会 "重组" 回到北边
The two halves would be separated by a demilitarized zone
一条中立区分隔了南北两边
until an election could be held
直到能够举行选举
to reunify North and South Vietnam,
重新统一南北越南
an election everyone knew Ho Chi Minh would win.
每个人都知道胡志明将会赢得选举
日内瓦协议规定了在两年内举行大选
以重新统一国家
大家都相信了
没人想到它会持续20多年
阮文松
越盟
我到北越接受训练
为的就是有天能解放南部
但我怎么也想不到战争会如此残酷
阮泰鹏
越盟
那种残暴难以想象
We had started walking up
我们开始往上走了
and we had probably gotten about a third of the way up the hill
我们大概走到了山丘1/3高的地方
卡尔·马兰提斯
陆战队
and then they unleashed on us.
然后他们开始袭击我们
We were in the middle of this horrible shit sandwich.
我们就像是这块恐怖三明治的中间夹心
That's what we called it.
我们就这样叫它
One of the things that I learned in the war is that
我在战争中学到了一件事情
we're not the top species on the planet
我们不是这星球上的顶级物种
because we're nice.
因为我们已经很客气了
People talk a lot about how well the military turns, you know,
人们常说军队如何把孩子
kids into, you know, killing machines and stuff.
变成杀戮机器之类的
And I'll always argue that it's just finishing school.
而我总说这只是完成学业而已
Braving the dangers
开着摇晃的小船
of the open sea in tiny, rickety craft,
勇敢面对危险的公海
thousands of Roman Catholic and Buddhist faith
上万名天主教和佛教徒
have found life impossible under the communists.
发现他们无法在共产主义下生活
For them, it's freedom or nothing.
对他们来说 不自由无所有
Under the Geneva Accords,
根据日内瓦协议
civilians living in either half of Vietnam
越南两边的平民
who wanted to relocate to the other
都可以在300天内
would have 300 days to do so.
自愿搬到另一边
My mother and father wanted to stay
我爸妈都想留下来
and meet my sister Thang again
再次看看我姐姐棠
because they knew Thang would come back.
因为他们知道棠会回来的
But on the other hand they couldn't risk that.
但另一方面他们又冒不起这个险
They were convinced that when Ho Chi Minh
胡志明政府来到河内时
and his government arrived in Hanoi,
他们都被定为有罪了
my father would be the first one to be killed
我的父亲将是第一个被杀死的人
and all of us would be persecuted.
我们所有人都会受到迫害
And I remember the day we left.
我记得我们离开的那天
I looked around and I thought, "I never come back here again."
我环顾了四周心想 "我再也回不来了"
It was extremely traumatic.
那是极大的创伤
It was like the ground was suddenly cut from under you.
突然间就无依无靠了
In the end, some 900,000 refugees,
最后大约有90万难民
including more than half of all the Catholics living in the North,
包括一半以上居住在北边的基督教徒
fled to the South,
都逃往了南边
many of them aboard American ships.
他们许多人登上了美国的船只
The United States hoped somehow to encourage the building
美国想以某种方式鼓励南越
of a legitimate government in the South.
建立起一个合法的政府
That government was now headed by Ngo Dinh Diem.
现在南越政府由吴廷琰领导
Both a Roman Catholic and a Confucian
他既是罗马天主教徒 也是孔教徒
in a largely Buddhist country,
而这个国家里大多是佛教徒
he was a celibate bachelor
他是个单身主义者
who had once planned to be a priest.
曾经还想成为一名牧师
The war for us really started when we became the partner,
我们的战争始于我们开始跟他合作
or I would say the victim, of President Diem.
或说是我们成为吴总统的受害者
We were going to help him turn South Vietnam into a democracy.
我们要帮他把南越变成民主制
莱斯利·吉尔伯
国防部
That's what he said he wanted to do.
他说这就是他想做的
And we believed him.
我们相信了他
Like Ho Chi Minh,
和胡志明一样
Diem had spent years abroad seeking support
吴廷琰也长年在国外寻求人们支持
for his own brand of Vietnamese nationalism.
他个人版本的越南民族主义
He was a veteran politician
他从军中退伍后从事政治
whose loathing for the French
他对法国人的厌恶
was matched only by his hatred for the communists,
不亚于他对共产主义的痛恨
who had imprisoned him
前者曾将他逮捕入狱
and buried alive his eldest brother and his nephew.
后者曾活埋他的长兄和侄子
Diem was aloof, autocratic,
吴廷琰既孤傲又独断
mistrustful of anyone much beyond his own family.
不信任自己家族之外的任何人
He also proved to be shrewd, resourceful,
他也十分精明和机智
and skilled at exploiting the weaknesses of his opponents.
善于利用对手的弱点
But he faced a daunting task in creating a new country.
但他面临着创建一个新国家的艰巨任务
The French, who still had thousands of troops
法国人在南方仍驻扎着上万军队
detested Diem.
且还不待见吴廷琰
Several provinces were under the sway of religious sects
有几个省份仍受控于宗教派别
with armies of their own.
且拥有自己的军队
Tens of thousands of Viet Minh soldiers had gone north,
数十万的越盟士兵都回到了北方
but several thousand cadre...
但仍有几千名骨干成员没回
trained and dedicated Communist Party workers...
这些训练有素且献身共产党的工人们
had stayed behind to organize resistance in the countryside.
还留在南方的乡下组织抵抗活动
And Saigon itself was ruled by the Binh Xuyen,
西贡则处在平川派的统治下
a crime syndicate backed by the French.
这是受法国支持的一个犯罪组织
And the French were behind the Binh Xuyen,
法国在平川派背后
sort of supporting them
类似于在支持他们
because they didn't want Diem to succeed.
因为他们不想让吴廷琰得逞
鲁弗斯·菲利普斯
中情局
And that became the central contest.
于是这成了争论的焦点
Some in the CIA believed that
中情局里的一些人认为
Diem could be the savior of South Vietnam.
吴廷琰将会是南越的救世主
Others were not so sure.
其他人则没这么确定
"He is a messiah without a message,"
"他可不是真正的救世主"
one diplomat reported to Washington.
有位外交官向华府这样报告
The U.S. ambassador agreed.
美国大使也认同此言
On April 27, 1955,
1955年4月27日
President Eisenhower decided to end
艾森豪威尔总统决定终止
American support for Diem's regime.
美国对吴廷琰政权的支持
But then Diem made an all-out assault
但随后吴廷琰开始全面
on the Binh Xuyen syndicate.
进攻平川派
Suddenly in the middle of the day
突然在那天中午
we heard gunfire and then we saw flames
我们听见了枪声 看到了火焰
and the neighborhood was burning.
街区着火烧了起来
There are hundreds of dead and wounded on both sides
双方都有成百上千人的伤亡
as the street fighting continues for an entire week.
这场街头战斗持续了一整个星期
For the United States,
对美国来说
the situation presents a grave problem.
这局势显然是一个严重的问题
Diem finally regains control of Saigon.
吴廷琰最终取得了西贡的控制权
In the end, Diem's forces prevailed.
最后吴廷琰的部队胜利了
Eisenhower now saw no option
艾森豪威尔现在别无选择
but to stick with Diem.
只能绑定吴廷琰了
The French then announced their intention
法国随后宣布说他们即将
to withdraw completely from South Vietnam,
完全撤出南越
ending nearly a century of occupation.
结束这近一个世纪的占领
Diem became wildly popular
吴廷琰变得很受欢迎
because he seemed to embody the nationalist cause in the South.
因为他似乎代表了南方的民族主义事业
He succeeded in getting the French
他成功地让法国人
out of Vietnam all the way.
完全地离开了越南
And Ho Chi Minh had only got them out of the northern half.
而胡志明只能让他们撤出北部半个越南
Flush with victory,
旗开得胜后
Diem called for a referendum in the South.
吴廷琰要求在南方举行公投
The CIA warned him not to meddle too much with the returns.
中情局警告他不要过于贪心地要回报
But when the ballots were counted,
但是在计算选票时
Diem claimed to have won 98.2% of the vote.
吴廷琰宣称他赢得了98.2%的选票
On October 26, 1955,
1955年10月26日
Ngo Dinh Diem named himself the first president
吴廷琰宣布自己为全新的
of the brand-new Republic of Vietnam.
越南共和国的第一任总统
The election to reunify the North and South that had been promised at Geneva
在日内瓦所承诺的统一南北的大选
would never be held.
将不再举行
He became our ally,
他成了我们的盟友
or rather our master,
或说是我们的主人
because the goal of preventing the communists
因为我们过分关注于
from taking over the South was so strong
阻止共产主义接管南越
that we couldn't afford for him to lose.
于是我们没法任由他失败
So Diem started to boss us around.
所以吴廷琰就开始调配我们了
And this was a typical relationship.
这就是一种典型的关系
You need any ally you believe
你需要自己能信任的盟友
to be the centerpiece of your foreign policy.
来成为你的外交政策的中心装饰品
They understand that right away.
他们一下子就明白了
And the tail wags the dog.
于是小人掌大权
From the Far East comes a distinguished visitor.
从远东来了位特殊的访客
President Ngo Dinh Diem of Vietnam is accorded
越南的吴廷琰总统受到了
one of President Eisenhower's rare airport greetings,
艾森豪威尔总统少有的机场接待
as he arrives for a four-day state visit.
他将进行为期四天的国事访问
President Diem, one of America's staunchest allies in Southeast Asia,
吴总统是美国在东南亚最坚实的盟友
will seek an increase in aid to shore up his country
他将寻求增加对他国家的援助
against increasing communist pressure,
以抗击愈发严峻的共产主义压力
a request to which the president lends a sympathetic ear.
我们的总统将体谅地倾听他的请求
Most politicians, Democrats as well as Republicans,
大多数民主党和共和党的政客
now seemed to share the changing views
现在似乎都跟参议员肯尼迪
of Senator John F. Kennedy.
一样改变了看法
South Vietnam is "our offspring," he said.
他说南越是 "我们的幼苗"
"We cannot abandon it."
"我们不能抛弃他"
If it fell, the United States would be "held responsible
如果它失败了 那么美国就会 "担负责任
and our prestige in Asia will sink to a new low."
我们在亚洲的声望也会降到新的谷底"
There had never before been a South Vietnamese nation,
此前从未有过一个南越国家
but Americans, who had rebuilt much of
但美国人曾在新政期间
their own country during the New Deal
重建了国内的许多地方
and had helped rebuild Western Europe
也曾通过马歇尔计划
through the Marshall Plan,
帮助了西欧战后重建
were convinced they could build one nonetheless.
相信再建个南越也不难
Eisenhower ordered scores of
艾森豪威尔命令了
American civilians to South Vietnam,
许多美国平民到南越
full of plans for economic development
带去了各种经济发展计划
meant to win, he hoped, the hearts and minds of the Vietnamese people.
他希望这能赢得越南人的民心
But those civilians would always
但这些平民的数量总是
be outnumbered by military advisors,
没有派去的军事顾问多
with orders to modernize, train, and equip Diem's forces,
后者受命来帮吴廷琰现代化训练和装备军队
now called the Army of the Republic of Vietnam...
现在他的军队叫做越南共和国军
the ARVN.
简称 南越国军
Some ARVN officers found American methods
一些国军军官发现美国人的方法
unsuited to the guerrilla war they expected to wage against the communists.
并不适用于他们与共产党的游击战
Most American military advisors
大多数的美国军事顾问
were veterans of the war in Korea,
都是韩战老兵
determined to prepare South Vietnamese forces
他们决心要让南越国军准备好
to slow a conventional invasion from the North.
抵挡住北方的常规入侵
But no one in North Vietnam
但北越从来就没有
was planning a conventional invasion.
准备进行常规入侵
Ho Chi Minh was focused on rebuilding his country,
胡志明正着眼于重建他的
devastated by more than a decade of war.
饱受了十多年的战争摧残的国家
The communists imposed brutal land reforms
共产党进行了残酷的土地革命
modeled on those underway in China
仿照的是中国正在进行的土改
with a ruthlessness that left thousands of people dead,
这无情地导致了数千人的死亡
including not only landlords who had sided with the French,
其中既有支持法国的地主
but also many villagers who had fought with the Viet Minh.
也有许多和越盟并肩作战的村民
Ho Chi Minh was still determined to reunite Vietnam.
胡志明仍决定要重新统一越南
But he worried that if he took direct military action against the South,
不过他担心对南方直接采取军事行动的话
the United States would be drawn more deeply into the struggle.
美国将会更深地介入到这场斗争里
He cautioned his comrades in the South to
他告诫南方的同志
put their faith in political agitation
要相信政治煽动的力量
and avoid violence.
并避免暴力手段
But that message rang hollow among
但这消息听来却有些空洞
embattled Southern revolutionaries struggling
因为四面楚歌的南方革命者正挣扎着
to survive under Diem's increasingly harsh regime.
活过吴廷琰日益严苛的政权
In a campaign he called "Denounce the Communists,"
在一场所谓的 "谴责共党" 运动中
Diem had imprisoned tens of thousands of citizens without trial
吴廷琰未经审判就逮捕了上万名平民
and ordered the executions of hundreds more.
并下令处死了上百人
Now, the communists took matters into their own hands
现在这些共产党人决定自行做主
and began attacking South Vietnamese officials.
开始攻击南越的官员
当时我们没有枪
所以我们用砍刀去杀那些暴政者
在起义中
我们杀死了一名安全官员
我们12个人都拿着砍刀
黎关公
越盟
他跑走掉进了稻田里
我们就把他砍死了
然后我们告诉人们
如果有人敢去参加他的葬礼
那也会被我们杀死
所以就没人敢去了
As violence in South Vietnam intensified,
随着南越的暴力冲突加剧
new leaders emerged in Hanoi.
河内出现了新的领导层
Ho Chi Minh would remain the face of the revolution around the world,
胡志明仍是面向世界的革命门面
but he now began to share power
但他现在要把权力分享给
with men who were growing impatient with his caution,
那些对他的谨慎越来越没耐心的人
men about whom Americans knew almost nothing.
美国对这些新人几乎一无所知
The most important proved to be a carpenter's son
其中最重要的一名是个木匠的儿子
from Quang Tri province in the South named Le Duan.
他来自南方的广治省 名叫黎筍
He had helped found the Indochinese Communist Party,
他曾帮助创立了印度支那共产党
survived nearly ten years in a French prison,
在法国监狱里待了近十年
and proved himself a shrewd political infighter
他是一个精明的政治斗争者
as he rose to become First Secretary of the party.
所以一路升至党内第一书记
我第一次见到黎筍是在1951年
我当时是个小干部
我看到他和其他领导人很不一样
他能理解南方同志们的意愿
阮玉
越盟
黎筍把他们的意愿带回了北方
政治局 河内
By 1959,
到1959年
Le Duan and his hardline allies
黎筍和他的强硬派盟友
were gaining influence within the North Vietnamese Politburo
在北越政治局里的影响力越来越大
and beginning to change its policy.
并开始改变了北越的政策
They now argued that Hanoi should do everything within its power
他们争论说河内应该用尽一切力量
to help Southern revolutionaries remove Diem by force.
帮助南越的革命同志武力除掉吴廷琰
北越采取了更为攻势的姿态
他们不接受国家这样子的分裂
他们想要这个国家
裴琰
南越外交官
重新统一
且不惜一切代价
Now, bands of 40 to 50 armed Viet Minh
现在40到50支武装的越盟小队
began slipping back home into South Vietnam,
开始偷偷溜进南越
following jungle paths hacked through the Laotian mountains
他们所走的老挝山区的丛林小道
that the Americans would soon call the Ho Chi Minh Trail.
将很快地被美国人称作胡志明小道
Violence against the Diem regime steadily accelerated.
针对吴廷琰政权的暴力活动稳步上升
On the evening of July 8, 1959,
1959年7月8日晚上
at Bien Hoa,
在边和市
20 miles northeast of Saigon,
就在西贡东北方20英里外
six American military advisors
6名美国顾问正在他们的
were watching a movie in their mess hall.
食堂里看着电影
Viet Minh guerrillas, who had crept silently into the compound,
越盟的游击队员悄悄地溜进基地里
opened fire through the windows.
通过窗户向内开火
Major Dale Buis from Pender, Nebraska,
来自内布拉斯加州彭德的少校戴尔·比伊斯
and Master Sergeant Chester Ovnand from Copperas Cove, Texas,
和来自德州科珀勒斯科夫的军士长切斯特·奥文南
were killed.
中弹身亡
They were the first American soldiers
他们是越南战争中第一批
to die from enemy fire in the Vietnam War.
死于敌军火力的美国士兵
We must prove all over again, to a watching world,
我们站在一个最为显眼的舞台上
as we sit on a most conspicuous stage,
我们必须在举世共睹下再次证明
whether this nation, conceived as it is
这个国家是否还有人们所认为的
with its freedom of choice, its breadth of opportunity, its range of alternatives,
选择的自由 广泛的机会 抉择的范围
can compete with the single-minded advance of the communist system.
来抗衡共产主义制度的坚决推进
On November 8, 1960,
1960年11月8日
John Fitzgerald Kennedy was elected president of the United States.
约翰·菲茨杰拉德·肯尼迪当选为美国总统
His vice president was Senator Lyndon Johnson.
他的副总统是参议员林登·约翰逊
They had narrowly beaten Vice President Richard Nixon
他们险胜了副总统理查德·尼克松
and his running mate, Senator Henry Cabot Lodge.
以及搭档参议员亨利·卡伯特·洛奇
During the campaign, both Kennedy and Nixon had
在竞选中 肯尼迪和尼克松都
pledged to hold the line against international communism
承诺会坚守对抗国际共产主义的阵线
wherever it seemed to be a threat.
而不管它是否有威胁性
But very few Americans knew or cared about
但很少有美国人知道或关心
what was going on in Vietnam.
越南发生了什么
Six weeks after Kennedy's election,
肯尼迪当选六周后
at a remote jungle village called Tan Lap
在靠近柬埔寨边境的一座
near the Cambodian border,
偏远丛林山村新立村
representatives of southern revolutionary groups
南越革命团体的代表们
met to form a new organization to replace the Viet Minh,
齐聚建立一个新组织以取代越盟
dedicated to overthrowing Ngo Dinh Diem
并致力于推翻吴廷琰
and ousting the foreigners supporting him.
赶走支持他的外国人
Behind the scenes, Le Duan and his communist comrades in Hanoi
背后里 黎筍及其在河内的同志
were orchestrating everything.
策划着这一切
The new organization would be called
这个新组织将叫做
the National Liberation Front...
民族解放阵线
the NLF.
简称 南民解
The armed wing of the NLF was called
南民解的军队叫做
the People's Liberation Armed Forces,
人民解放武装力量
but its enemies in Saigon and Washington preferred
但其在西贡和华府的敌人们
a more disparaging term.
更喜欢蔑视地称呼他们
In their eyes, the revolutionaries were
在他们眼中 这些革命者都是
Communist Traitors to the Vietnamese Nation...
越南国家的共产主义叛徒
the Viet Cong.
简称 越共
我们的领导人说 "我们愿意牺牲至最后一名越南人"
我们为这些口号而欢欣鼓舞
人们没有完全理解
辉德
北越
在这些英雄口号的背后
将是他们自己的牺牲
历史自会评判这场战争
是否值得这么多的牺牲
Let every nation know,
让每个国家都知道
1961年1月20日
whether it wishes us well or ill,
不论它们希望我们繁荣还是衰落
that we shall pay any price,
我们会付出一切代价
bear any burden,
承受一切负担
meet any hardship,
迎接一切艰难
support any friend,
支持一切朋友
oppose any foe,
反对一切敌人
to assure the survival and the success of liberty.
来确保自由的存在与胜利
For me, I'd always thought of courage
我一直以为勇气是
as charging enemy bunkers
冲进敌人堡垒
or standing up under fire.
或屹立于炮火中
But just to walk,
但光是走起来
day after day from village to village
一天天地走 从这村到那村
and through the paddies and up into the mountains,
穿过稻田 爬上山林
just to get up in the morning and look out at the land
光是早上起来 望向大地
and think, "In a few minutes I'll be walking out there
想着 "过几分钟我就会走到那里了
蒂姆·奥布莱恩
陆军
and will my corpse be there, over there?
我的尸体会不会就倒在那里呢
Will I lose a leg out there?"
我会在外面那里失去一条腿吗"
Just to walk felt incredibly brave.
光是走起来就觉得非常勇敢了
I would sometimes look at my legs as I walked,
我有时走路会看着自己的双脚
thinking, how am I doing this?
想着我怎么会来做这个呢
翻译: @lsmlive
暴雨将至-鲍勃·迪伦
A Hard Rain's A-Gonna Fall by Bob Dylan
你都去了哪里 我的蓝眼孩子
Oh, where have you been, my blue-eyed son?
你都去了哪里 我的亲爱小孩
Oh, where have you been, my darling young one?
我曾磕磕绊绊越过12座迷蒙山峰
I’ve stumbled on the side of twelve misty mountains
我曾走走爬爬路过6条蜿蜒公路
I’ve walked and I’ve crawled on six crooked highways
我曾进进出出经过7座伤心树林
I’ve stepped in the middle of seven sad forests
我曾面对十几片的死海
I’ve been out in front of a dozen dead oceans
我曾深入一万里的墓地
I’ve been ten thousand miles in the mouth of a graveyard
暴雨啊 暴雨啊
And it’s a hard, and it’s a hard,
it’s a hard, and it’s a hard
暴雨将至
And it’s a hard rain’s a-gonna fall
你都见过什么 我的蓝眼孩子
Oh, what did you see, my blue-eyed son?
你都见过什么 我的亲爱小孩
Oh, what did you see, my darling young one?
我见过新生的婴儿被野狼围住
I saw a newborn baby with wild wolves all around it
我见过钻石的公路却无人行走
I saw a highway of diamonds with nobody on it
我见过黑色的树枝上滴淌鲜血
I saw a black branch with blood that kept drippin’
我见过满屋的人握着锤子流血
I saw a room full of men with their hammers a-bleedin’
我见过白色的梯子淹没入水中
I saw a white ladder all covered with water
我见过说话的万人都舌头不全
I saw ten thousand talkers whose tongues were all broken
我见过年轻的孩子在舞枪弄剑
I saw guns and sharp swords in the hands of young children
暴雨啊 暴雨啊
And it’s a hard, and it’s a hard,
it’s a hard, and it’s a hard
暴雨将至
And it’s a hard rain’s a-gonna fall
暴雨啊 暴雨啊
And it’s a hard, and it’s a hard,
it’s a hard, and it’s a hard
暴雨将至
And it’s a hard rain’s a-gonna fall